Ignition [music] sequence start
all engines up.
>> It's good to have an aviator and
astronaut in charge. Jared Eisen,
>> the new NASA administrator.
>> NASA's still hot. Humankind [music] will
not be contained to planet Earth
indefinitely. In the next giant leap
capabilities, that's nuclear power and
propulsion. That's what extends
America's reach farther into the solar
system. That's what guarantees the third
race will never be in question.
Please welcome Jared Isaacman.
[music]
Good morning everyone. It is an absolute
honor to be here at Allin.
We are living through an extraordinary
moment in history, aren't we? It took
just 65 years from Orville and Wilbur's
first flight to Neil and Buzz walking on
the surface of the moon. Now, it's been
57 years since Apollo 11. And for a
while there, pace of progress hasn't
been all that inspiring, but look at
what is on the horizon right now. We got
artificial intelligence, quantum
technologies,
robotics, additive manufacturing, the
promise of fusion energy, biotech to
heal the disabled, autonomous
transportation, this whole abundance
thing everyone's talking about, all
converging in the years ahead is beyond
what most people can comprehend. Our
world will fundamentally change. how we
live, how we work, how we fight wars,
how we reach out and touch the stars.
But we are not alone on this journey. We
are living through a great power
competition. Other nations understand
the opportunities that can elevate
nations and change civilizations. And
perhaps nowhere are the possibilities,
the competition, and the consequences of
getting it wrong more apparent than in
the ultimate high ground above us. Now
at NASA, we are doing things differently
and we are regaining our swagger and
putting wins on the board. But absent
this president, absent this geopolitical
competition and the very real
possibility of losing the second space
race, I suspect very little would have
changed. For too long, resources at the
world's most accomplished space agency
were spread everywhere, trying to make
everyone happy. Much of it was through
external imposition, but plenty of it
was self-inflicted. We partnered for the
sake of partnerships, oftent times
becoming a drag on the mission instead
of accelerating it. As a result, we have
the Orion spacecraft that we can't
inject into low lunar orbit like we did
during Apollo. And the prior
administration cancelled the Mars sample
return mission that was on track to cost
more than an aircraft carrier. We
created programs that were too big to
fail fail, too costly to truly succeed
in the hope that they would survive
administrations. The results being a
rocket that was designed when China was
predominantly operating coal fired
locomotives and now becoming operational
as China operates 25,000 mi of highspeed
rail and is just a few years away from
their own Apollo 11 like moment. core
competencies and tens of thousands of
the NASA workforce were rented,
outsourced, or lost, which turned what
should have been months worth of
progress into years at tremendously
greater cost. Eventually, too little was
left to do things the right way. The way
NASA showed the world how to do it in
decades past. So, we invented this whole
dream state as a service thing, forgoing
the playbook of success and shifting the
impossible burden onto others.
The result is that our moon rocket is in
fact less efficient than Saturn 5 at
converting launch mass into payload head
payload headed for the moon with more
time between the Aremis 1 and Artemis 2
mission than all 12 of the Geminy
missions that were flown 60 years
before. A lunar space station that
whenever it may have been delivered put
our astronauts in a position to look
down on the most desirable lunar real
estate instead of operating on the
surface and occupying it. one XPlane
that wasn't flying very much and
billions spent on failed nuclear
programs that had not left the
laboratory since 1965.
Now, during the first space race, we
were slow out of the gate, but NASA
ultimately ran up the score. The second
will be much closer than it ever needed
to be. Since becoming the administrator
of LA NASA last year, we have made a
different choice. We are not going to
try and make everyone happy. we are not
going to spread every penny across every
district or partner with every nation
just to try and make everyone happy or
because that's how people incorrectly
believed it always was. I am certainly
not here for the money to favor
companies for the title, the notoriety,
the politics. I'm not here to be your VC
to entertain your dream or invent new
markets if it detracts in the slightest
way from the missions that we have been
entrusted to achieve on behalf of the
American people. You can take those
conversations up with the Department of
Commerce if you like. I'm here to
execute on President Trump's national
space policy to align and focus
resources to work alongside and unleash
this best the best this nation has to
offer. From the NASA workforce to our
industry to our partners and deliver the
world changing outcomes. The kind of
outcomes that put Neil and Buzz on the
moon. The kind of outcomes that inspired
many of you to be in this room in the
first place. This is a very
reinvigorated and energized NASA and
America is back in the business of
sending our astronauts to the moon.
[applause]
Now, Artemis 2 was just the beginning.
Those four heroic astronauts, recent
recipients of the Congressional Space
Medal of Honor, rode 8.8 8 million
pounds of thrust to near Earth escape
velocities, traveled farther into space
than any humans in history around the
moon and back home safely. And that was
just the opening act. We are not waiting
3 years to fly again. We are not turning
every rocket into a work of art. Artemis
3 is already being assembled right now
at a pace many doubted was possible just
months ago. Before year end, we intend
to roll out to launch complex 39B for a
tanking test and send a message to our
workforce, our industry, and our rivals
overseas. NASA is back and we are not
going to sit idly by. We are not just a
procurement organization. We are going
to do the extremely demanding work and
achieve our objectives safely,
responsibly, and urgently because that
is what meeting the moment requires.
Now, in the summer of 2027, Artemis 3
will launch on SLS into low Earth orbit
and rendevous with lander test vehicles
from Blue Origin and SpaceX in what will
be a remarkable display of the three
most powerful rockets and spacecraft in
the world. We will test interoperability
and show what a future multilaunch
campaign can actually look like. What we
learn will inform the uncrrewed test
landings that follow. and then Artemis 4
in 2028 when American astronauts return
to the lunar surface and this time to
stay. In parallel
[applause]
in parallel we are establishing
humanity's first outpost on another
world, a moon base. And this time we are
leveraging the NASA playbook of decades
past. We are not jumping directly to the
dream state. We will launch missions on
a near monthly cadence and undertake the
science of survival. That means
autonomous and crude mobility, surface
improvement, [snorts] institute resource
util utilization and manufacturing,
logistics, habitability, power,
communications, and all the science
instruments the mass budget affords. We
will bring it to you live and HD on the
moonbased website. And we will leave no
doubters this time. We go for the
scientific and the economic potential.
we go to learn about the formation of
our solar system, but primarily because
the lunar south pole, where the water
ice is, is going to be the technological
proving ground for where we inevitably
go next, which is Mars.
In 2028,
[applause]
in 2028, NASA will leave decades and
billions of dollars of failed nuclear
programs behind and launch SR1 Freedom,
a 100 kilowatt fision reactor that will
finally get America underway on nuclear
power. The mission will transit Mars and
release Skyfall, which carries three
Ingenuity class helicopters and using
ground penetrating radar to scout
subsurface ice and future landing sites.
This will mark the beginning of the
nuclear NASA, pivoting our workforce and
facilities back to doing the near
impossible. Missions with no obvious
business case, what no company, no
agency or nation is presently capable of
accomplishing, but but that extend
humanity's reach farther into the outer
solar system. And just during like just
like during the Apollo era, the
technology that we pioneer to get there
will surely benefit life back here at
home. There will be lots of nuclear
missions. SR2, SR3, SR4. Alongside our
industry partners, we will push the
boundaries of high temperature
materials, more efficient power
conversion, more reduced radiator mass,
and higher performance electric
propulsion as we visit some of the most
interesting moons like Enceladus,
Europa, and Titan. These are worlds with
oceans, with complex chemistry, and
perhaps the ingredients for life. a
reminder that some of the greatest
discoveries in human history, they may
be waiting for us in our own backyard.
We could answer the question, are we
alone? And are we alone even in our own
solar system, let alone the galaxy and
universe around us? Someday, a
chemically augmented nuclearpowered
transfer vehicle, part of an American
starfleet, supported by a armada of
starships and other spacecraft, will
carry humans to the surface of Mars and
bring them home safely to tell us about
it. And not just once. We are on this
great destiny of human exploration, and
we are not turning back. Along the way,
we are going to do the other things.
Commercial satellites are being printed
off at a rate that will help us
affordably understand the only planet
that we presently inhabit, our home star
and space weather, and better predict
weather and perhaps respond to to
wildfires and natural disasters better,
freeing up more resources to build the
exquisite flagship science missions that
only NASA can undertake. Like, for
example, the nuclearpowered Dragonfly
Octter. It's powered by a 2 kilowatt
MMRTG, converting to just 100 watts of
electricity, barely better than an old
light bulb, but it will journey to
Saturn's moon of Titan in 2028. Europa
Clipper will arrive at Jupiter's icy
moon in 2030.
And our great space telescopes like
James Webb and Hubble will soon be
joined by Roman. And with her nearly 300
megapixel widefield instrument and JPL
built coronagraph, in the moments ahead,
Roman will open her eyes. And in that
instance, she will see more of the
universe than any scientific instrument
we've ever put in space before. Her
surveys will seek to
it is a cool telescope. [applause]
Her surveys will seek to understand the
mysteries of dark energy and dark matter
and reveal tens of thousands of worlds
that are hidden behind in distant stars.
Roman will return images so large and in
such detail there is no screen on Earth
large enough to display them. Now other
missions like Neo Surveyor will find
asteroids and comets that can threaten
Earth. While next generation telescopes
in development will seek out habitable
planets orbiting other stars. The last
few decades have shown us that the
future in space that we all imagined as
children will never be realized if
they're perpetually funded by taxpayers.
NASA will do everything within reason to
support an orbital and perhaps even
lunar economy someday, building on the
proven markets of launch, observation,
and communication. Whether the next
frontier is in orbital data centers or
commercial space stations or on orbit
manufacturing, regulith resource
extraction, asteroid mining, or
industries that none of us have even
imagined yet. Now, it's not NASA's job
to force an economy, but we will do all
we can to ignite one as we pursue our
missions. And in the service of the
first A and NASA, we are rebuilding our
XPlane fleet. The X59 is researching
quiet supersonic flight. But it's just
the beginning as NASA recommmits to
flight test and works alongside industry
to push the boundaries of airframe and
propulsion design. It will not be long
before NASA is flying once again as high
and as fast as we have from decades
past. and then even more.
But if this frontier is going to expand
as rapidly as we believe it will be, we
will have to cultivate the talent to
lead it, the space domain deserves an
institution focused on that future and
call it what many already have and
should, a Starfleet Academy. That is why
the president established the commission
for the United States Space Academy, a
NASA federal academy to prepare the next
generation of astronauts, scientists,
engineers, technicians, operators,
pilots, and leaders. And just as the
need for space force became clear as the
domain evolved, we should be equally
forward-looking and preparing
those who will build the moon base,
operate nuclearpowered spacecraft,
command missions to Mars, ensure our
national security, and create industries
in orbit we can barely imagine today.
And there is no time to waste. I want
you all to think about where you were
when Artemis 2 astronauts sent back
those images from the moon. Who did it
touch? your parents, your friends, your
colleagues, your children. Now, I want
you to imagine astronauts climbing down
the ladder. Only this time, it is not
grainy black and white footage from July
20th, 1969. It's highdefinition color
streaming live to billions of people all
around the world. The astronaut steps
foot on the lunar surface. The camera
pans up and the flag on the spacuit is
not American. There will be no footnote
explaining that we spent more. No
disclaimer that our architecture was
complicated. No one will care how many
studies we completed, how many meetings
we held, what congressional districts
benefited, who all the all-star
lobbyists were for their hardware, who
served on the committee, or how many
times we slipped the schedule for what
someone thought was a perfectly
reasonable reason. The world will just
see who got there. China intends to put
their astronauts on the moon by 2030.
Its robotic missions are targeting the
Shackleton crater of the lunar south
pole next year and there are only so
many good parking spots in that
neighborhood and they intend to occupy
them. They are working with Russia on
their own nuclearpowered moon base. And
to be clear, China will accomplish what
the Soviets never could during the first
space race. They have a very achievable
two launch architecture, the national
will and capabilities to put their
astronauts on the surface of the moon.
And if America has not returned despite
the decades of promises and the more
than 100 billion invested, the shock
wave will be felt around the world. Our
allies will notice. Our adversaries will
notice. Every nation deciding whose
technology to buy, whose standards to
adopt, whose security guarantees to
trust, and whose vision of the future
will to follow will take notice. And
perhaps most importantly, our children
will notice. That is why we must remain
focused on the objectives that matter.
Why NASA was established in the first
place. There is no time anymore for
lobbying against America's interests or
further tolerating the status quo. Only
extreme ownership, competence, and
action. Those of us inspired by the
pioneers and heroes of decades past know
they set the bar high. But we do not
honor them by living forever on what
they accomplished. This is our time to
pick up where they left off, return, and
never give up the moon again, and then
set our sights on Mars and beyond. And
none of this will be accomplished by
NASA alone. We have the support of
President Trump. We have Congress. We
have a clear mandate in the national
space policy. But it will take brilliant
entrepreneurs, scientists, engineers,
our allies, and Americans across the
country who still believe that great
nations can do great things. because our
children will either inherit the
confidence of a nation still capable of
the extraordinary or the memory of one
that used to be. That responsibility,
that choice belongs to all of us. And I
believe when history looks back on this
moment, let it record that America did
not hesitate any longer. We did not
allow the bureaucracy, the complacency,
the waste, inaction, or fear of failure
to constrain what we could accomplish.
We chose to go and we went. Thank you.
[applause]
All right,
let's go.
[music] Let's go. All right, everybody.
>> America. Good job. Good job. [music]
[music]
>> Where do you want me? Oh, right on the I
was commenting backstage on how uh easy
it is for NASA to come and do speeches
given the content the the capacity to
show visuals like this. Can you imagine
like housing and urban development
trying to do a presentation?
>> No, we have we have unbelievable
material to work with. I'm thankful
every day that I I don't lead uh the IRS
or social
>> Yeah. Right. Can we can we talk about um
we don't have a lot of time so I I I
know I want to move our way through the
universe but can we start with the moon
um what is is there a you know there's
kind of this case that NASA makes about
the new the moon being the starting
point for getting to Mars but is the
moon a potentially viable economy on its
own? Is there an industry to be built on
the moon? Is there an ongoing set of
operations
uh that could be established on the moon
that make sense beyond just kind of
testing equipment before we go to Mars?
>> Yeah, maybe. Right. So, I think we are
extremely fortunate. We've been gifted a
moon 3 days away to test out everything
we need on this great adventure of
discovery, right? I mean, this is where
you want to go to really dial in power.
Your spac suits. It's taken us decades
to build replacement spac suits from the
Apollo era. Let's test that out on the
moon. habitation modules certainly
insitue resource manufacturing robotics
right I mean you know look EVAs are
fantastic astronauts bouncing around on
the moon is going to be highly
inspirational that's like one of the
last things you should do when you have
a moon base is send somebody outside in
that extremely dangerous environment let
robotics do it and in order to
accomplish all of this you have to send
an extraordinary demand signal to
industry I mean over the next four years
we're talking dozens of landers dozens
of rovers lots of insitue resource
manufacturing experimentation you're
giving industry
all the opportunity in the world to
figure out how to unlock value from the
lunar regalith, right? But I can't
guarantee it, right? And that's my point
on the Department of Commerce. They have
a, you know, a whole space commerce
office that can can work through that.
I'm I am going to make sure that NASA,
you know, can master the skills
necessary to go to Mars for its
scientific potential. We'll put radio
telescopes on the far side to inspire
the next generation. And if along the
way it ignites a lunar economy, that's
fantastic. But it costs an awful lot to
get there. An awful lot to extract
resources.
>> Sorry, one sec. But and then we have to
map the South Pole to figure out where
we're going. Is that right? And that's
part of this promise mission. That's
kind of the next big mission for the
moon.
>> So uh I'm glad you brought up promise.
Uh so we uh we have mapped the lunar
south pole. There are only so many good
landing spots. And what do I mean by
that? I mean surface area of the moon is
like the size of Africa. The south pole
of the moon is like Washington DC. And
there's only so many good craters that
have these permanently shaded regions,
which by the way, I mean, that is a
harsher environment than Mars itself.
That's where the water ice is. But the
crater cliffs can also give you near
eternal access to light for solar power.
So there's only so many good landing
spots. And you think about when like a
vehicle the size of Starship comes down
lunar surface. Believe me, that's going
to blast out a little bit of craters,
send debris. So really limited uh uh
parking spots on that. Promise is very
awesome because Promise is a
radioisotope powered rover that we built
as a spare essentially for the two
rovers uh Perseverance and Curiosity are
on on on on the on Mars right now. And
just to give you a sense, this thing is
the size of like a jeep. Okay, so we
have some uh PU238 that's decaying right
now. You only get so much life out of
it. We want to take that, put it on
promise, and send it to the moon. and it
can go in and start prospecting in those
permanently shaded regions that I mean
almost any other hardware would die in.
It's a very good way to make use of
taxpayer dollars that have largely
already been spent.
>> And Jared, you were informing me last
night, informing me last night and
educating me on this specific southern
region of the of the moon being
absolutely critical for us to get to
first versus China. Why is it so
critical that we get there before China?
and what's it going to take to do that?
And just as a followup to that, what was
the state of NASA when you got there?
Because it did feel like they since the
space shuttle program haven't been super
focused or effective, but correct me if
I'm wrong.
>> Yeah. I mean, just to be clear, you're
you're talking about some of the best
best talent in this nation shows up to
work at NASA every day, and they want to
change the world in air and space. And
for a very long time, everybody was
trying to run NASA other than the people
themselves that show up to work there. I
mean, like I you heard from my remarks,
you know, let's make everyone happy.
Let's spread our resources to every
congressional district. Let's collect 25
different flags to partner on the next
mission that takes something that should
cost a couple billion, which is very
cool. Like going and getting samples
back from Mars that could lead to the
most consequential discovery in human
history, and layer a bunch of other
people on and make it cost more than a
carrier, and then it then it gets
canceled, right? So NASA's back in
charge now, right? We are in a space
race. People are giving us the latitude
to to do what we need to do. And as a
result, we are extremely focused on the
president's national space policy.
Return to the moon, build a base, get
underway in nuclear power and the other
things. And the workforce is responding
well. And I'm I'm grateful alongside
them. So we are in a different state
today. Unfortunately, we don't have the
time necessarily we'd like because years
were lost uh in this now uh new space
race. Now, the south pole of the moon,
again, we've been gifted a moon 3 days
away to again master those skills to go
to Mars. There's only so many good
sparking spots. The Chinese and the
Russians know that, right? They they
were going to launch a mission a couple
weeks ago right to the Shackleton Ridge.
Uh which, you know, maybe it was
mechanical, maybe it was weather
related, or maybe they were smart enough
to know that if they actually did do it,
it probably would ignite one hell of a a
fire and urgency in us. Uh but that
would have taken up one of like a couple
critical parking spots. They're going to
build a base there. They've partnered
with Russia. They're going to have a
fision power fision reactor there. And
they're going to do the exact same
things we are, which is interact with
the water ice and get very good. And
then where are they going next? The
third space race. They're going to go to
Mars. And then they'll have that massive
Neil Armstrong like moment that will
send a message around the world. And we
are very committed to not letting that
happen.
>> What is the big technological leap that
you have to make from the current course
in speed to actually make Mars more
realistic? Is it is it propulsion and
thrust is the main vector?
>> So I I think there's a I think there's a
a couple things there. Look, robotics
are going to be critical in all of this.
So uh if you if you chose a path that
was purely like chemical propulsion of
which you know vehicles like uh Starship
are going to be incredible at that.
Well, you will no doubt have the means
to send astronauts to Mars. uh they
they've already figured out habitability
a long time ago and you're talking very
comparable velocities whether you're
going to the to the moon or Mars in that
regard. The hard part is how do you come
back right? You're going to need to make
propellant on Mars to do so and you know
one solution to that to say is well I'll
have an army of robots that'll do it and
uh I'll have football field size you
know solar panels and then the robots
can dust them off from all the uh the
dust storms that'll happen and then
you'll make your own propellant you'll
come home. The hard part is it's really
it's really challenging to do that under
one atmosphere and 1G here on Earth. I
mean you can see how many people show up
at like stage zero at you know at
Starbase to launch a mission or and by
the way that is the right right way to
kind of win the war to put lots of mass
on the surface. Um NASA can help that by
kind of pivoting by stop doing what uh
what industry is already doing really
well and invest in that next giant leap
capabilities that have no obvious you
know business use case today which is
fision power [snorts] and then you can
have chemically augmented NEP spaceships
uh transfer vehicles and go to and from
Mars and you don't need to refuel them
until they come back and what you're
refilling is krypton or xenon. You're
not having to make propellant on the
surface of of uh of Mars. That to me is
how NASA works alongside industry to
invest in the capabilities that are
necessary for American leadership in
space. And by the way, those are the
capabilities you want to go to like
Saturn's moon of Enceladus, to go to
Titan, to go to Europa where you have
you have oceans on two of those moons
that that could have still life in them.
We don't know. How do you convince these
incredible learned people to work for
NASA versus SpaceX or other private
space companies now in a world where
there's so many ways in which you can
contribute?
>> So, so, so great. I'm I'm glad you asked
that because it's a double down on
nuclear, but it's right now we don't
have a a recruiting problem initially. I
mean, we take 1% uh of the intern
applications that go into our pathway
program which guarantee him a job at
NASA. Then the question is, can you
retain them? And if you're doing exactly
what SpaceX, Blue, Rocket Lab, Stoke,
ULA, and others are doing in industry,
except you're doing it off, you know,
you know, 50-y old shuttle hardware that
again is not as efficient from for
missions like going to the moon as
Saturn 5 was, you're going to lose that
workforce. So, what do you need to do?
You know when we have those near
impossible breakthroughs and there is a
business case like there certainly is
for launch where you can be one customer
many you hand it off to industry and you
pivot and that's how you retain talent
that can only do these type of missions
at NASA which is the nuclear NASA SR1 is
just the beginning that is our Nautilus
there will be a grand fleet of
nuclearpowered uh on the frontier
essentially you need to constantly keep
pivoting to the next new thing in the
>> can you explain just just really briefly
a primer on how nuclear works for
generating thrust
>> yeah sure so actually you And just think
of a lot of the uh like say Starlink
satellites that you'd have up right now
that use uh you hauler ion thrusters
right now. They're generating
electricity through solar power uh and
then they're using through uh
electromagnetic forces. They're they're
they're ionizing either krypton or xenon
and uh and then just basically
accelerating it out uh of the thruster
which gives you very very high uh you
know exhaust velocity. So it's extremely
efficient, very low thrust uh and you
can use that propellant for a very long
time. And and in space, the faster the
molecule shoots out the back, the more
thrust it generates for the for the
craft to move forward.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's just very low mass
that you're actually it's very low mass
flow, but highly efficient, right? So
very very efficient, high uh you know,
exhaust velocities. The idea though is
where that breaks down is the farther
you get away from the sun. So once you
get out towards Jupiter, I mean, solar
effectiveness is is negligible, right?
So what you're using is like a a a uh
the thermal energy from a a nuclear
reactor. So 100 kows will scale it up to
250 who knows maybe megawatt class,
right? You're going to want to run that
reactor as hot as you possibly can. So
that's your high temperature materials
and then you're going to convert it
through like a a closed braen cycle
power conversion unit into electricity
and that electricity is then going to
power those same thrusters that you
would see on Starlinks. It's just
they're scaled up, right? They're like
12 kow, then 14 kilow, 25 kow thrusters.
>> What is NASA's budget and if you could
have your brothers, what would it be?
Uh I'm uh incredibly supportive of look
I've said it I've said it many times
right now like NASA does not have a
topline problem like we are bad capital
allocators and have been for a long time
and a lot of that is based on NASA
choices it's based on what other people
forced us to do and that's changed we
have $25 billion I mean there's got how
many how many entrepreneurs are in this
room starv 25 billion is a lot of money
[laughter] you can build some pretty
incredible hardware you're one of the
few entrepreneurs that actually has
built a profitable company and taken it
You showed a picture of the uh blackbird
up there. And uh
>> you sure that's a blackbird?
>> Well, okay. Uh what was that picture
that you showed up there?
>> Like I said, NASA's getting back in the
business flying high and fast again.
>> I mean, that doesn't seem like a space
vehicle. It seems like a
earth air vehicle.
>> Yeah. So, uh the first A in NASA is our
is our aeronautics portfolio. And what
we've contributed to over the decades,
you may not realize this. Look, when you
go see an F-22 fly at an air show and
wow you, the flybywire technology was
us. The the, you know, thrust vectoring
technology was us. Uh NASA's been
contributing to breakthroughs in
aeronautics, both civil, commercial, and
national security applications for a
long time. And again, kind of similar to
the same theme, over the years, we've
been forced to spend our aeronautics
budget on like subsidizing high TRL uh
efforts from big prime contractors. An
engine that's 40 years old, they want to
squeak 3% more uh fuel efficiency out of
it. Get NASA to pay for it. I'm like,
are you kidding? There is no way we are
doing that. You can underwrite that
investment yourself for competitive
reasons. You know what I want to do? I
want to get back to the radical airframe
and engine designs like we were always
supposed to do. And you're getting a
little bit of a taste for that on the on
the
>> Tell us about the importance of having a
human on these ships when we go to the
moon, when we go to Mars versus if
Optimus figure these humanoid robotics
are ready. Why would we risk a human
life in these incredibly um dangerous
environments? Is it ego? Is it we're
trying to prove a point to have humans
in the loop on these is or should we
just be sending robots
>> or it's our it's our destiny, right? I
mean the same reason why we we cross the
oceans and seas and climb the mountains.
This is who we are. Would have many
people stopped uh pause from the the
discourse of our our daily lives uh to
look at those astronauts go around the
moon on Artemis 2 if they weren't
humans. I I don't think so. Now don't
get me wrong, we are going to need
robotics and there are some environments
that just whether it's the radiation
that we can only do uncrrewed um you
know robotic missions but we can we can
go to the moon as we've done before with
our astronauts, we can go to Mars and we
can continue on outward and robotics
will absolutely play a critical role in
that journey.
>> What about um then just like the
autonomous navigation systems you talked
about fly by wire? I mean, we still see
even just like last week the the
incident with Amazon Air. Now, this is
civil aviation, but the overrun is
ridiculous. That that that error mode
was pretty shocking to to people, I
think. Um,
how do we push better and safer
technologies and the more obvious
solutions, even if that may actually
disintermediate
uh human involvement?
>> Well, I'll just say that NASA's been
playing a role with uh air traffic
safety and modernization for a long
time. It was NASA that pioneered uh the
um autonomous ground collision avoidance
software. So I mean it's saved I mean
countless lives of fighter pilots pull
too many G's, they black out the point
the nose of the aircraft's point at the
ground, the aircraft recognizes it and
and safely recovers it. That was NASA uh
work. Um but I will I mean to to your
point and we are obviously very involved
as you think about a world that's going
to have who knows like millions of
drones flying around delivering us
medicine and other things like we we
have to work very closely with the FAA
on that. But I will tell you we are
thinking about uh you know uh AI and
autonomous uh applications within the
missions we're designing right now like
one mission going to Venus Da Vinci it
will not last long uh in that high
pressure environment right we are going
to only have so much time to gather as
much information as we can to update you
know kind of the trajectory of the
vehicle this is not interesting
disregard this is interesting I'm
turning in that direction we've already
tested this with some of our rovers on
Mars and I in my last dying breath this
is what I choose to send back uh you
know to the scientists on Earth to
understand this uh this environment and
that's just one step towards a direction
that will inevitably include more
autonomy in our in our crude and uncrude
spacecraft and how do you think about
allocation of capital resources Jared to
some of the scientific discovery uh the
the observational systems uh future
platforms for observational for deep
space research uh is there a view in
your mind it should be a 5% of budget
like how do you think about um
rationalizing where we go with the spend
there.
>> Yeah, I I mean I would say right now
science is uh approximately call it a
third of of NASA's budget. We recently
reorganized but your main mission
directorates right now are human space
exploration which covers both the great
work we're doing in the international
space station as well as missions to
example moon and building a moon base.
You have your research technology
mission directorate which is shouldering
most of the nuclear NASA effort. Uh and
then you have your science mission
directorate. And how I think about this
is like you have to take advantage of
commercial industry right now. Like
again there's no one would doubt that
launch observation communications are
real services where NASA is one customer
of many. You've got all these great
companies that are printing out
satellites again for Earth observation
whether it's for national security
reasons um you know or otherwise like
leverage it for agriculture le level it
leverage it for earth sciences give them
the instruments if necessary license it
to them free up resources to do what
industry is not going to want to take on
which is building a nuclearpowered
octicopter to go to Saturn's moon of
Titan so free up as much resource we can
to do that and I would always prioritize
getting new missions out there to unlock
the secrets of the universe there versus
the the researchers if we get the data
There'll be plenty of brilliant people
at institutions around the country that
will want to analyze it, but what's the
point if you can't uh launch those next
missions?
>> And as we wrap up, can we watch the
video of the helicopters on Mars and can
you just tell us about the timelines to
this um becoming reality for
>> Oh, absolutely.
>> Yeah.
>> So, here it is coming in. There it is.
>> Yeah. I mean, how cool is how cool is
this?
>> I mean, I'm telling you, you can't do
this at HUD
>> or IRS. Imagine IRS putting out a video.
I only made the Irish joke cuz I know
>> here's the auditor.
>> I mean, it is it is really incredible.
>> So, what's this what's the status of
this uh this program?
>> So, we tested one uh Ingenuity uh on our
our last rover mission to Mars. It did
fantastically well. I mean, can you
imagine this is near vacuum by the way
on Mars,
>> right? It's like a 10th atmosphere,
right?
>> You know, fractional that are that are
flying around. Now, we're going to send
three of these with ground penetrating
radars, uh which I think is just
awesome. But most importantly, how it
got there. It got there under nuclear
power. A true fisionpowered 100 kilowatt
spacecraft that flew by Mars and
released it. This will launch in 28. Uh
we believe the uh it's it's
approximately a year before the uh the
helicopters will get there. We're still
doing some some trades, but an
absolutely extraordinary mission and the
start of many more. I mean, again, think
about it. There is so much we can learn
on the moons within our own solar
system. Some really shocking discoveries
are just waiting for us in our own
backyard.
>> Are you going to test pilot the
blackbird? That's not the blackbird.
[laughter]
We have a lot of talented folks.
>> Hey Jared, you um you mentioned China,
>> all levels of the organization.
>> Exactly. [laughter] All of the or
including the head of the organization
is quitear quite a pilot. I
>> I know we got a wrap, but you mentioned
China and Russia collaborating together.
Just wanted to double click on that.
>> What are their capabilities? Russia
can't even take Keev. Uh and like
they've been out of war for four years.
Are they capable of getting to space and
doing anything of material? I and I mean
this genuinely in a very
>> please come back
>> but then China is copying a lot of what
um you don't have to listen to Chimath.
Um this is a serious question. China is
copying a lot of what Elon's doing in
real time.
>> Yes. And what's their actual capability
if we assume Russia is up against it and
they're broke? And am I correct that
Russia's up against it and they're
broke? I would just say I mean look
obviously have a great appreciation for
the history of the the Russian and
Soviet space program. I mean like I said
in my remarks they came out of the gate
hot first you know astronaut in orbit
first spacew walk they've done a lot of
great things and they contribute to us
contribute with us today and collaborate
on the international space station but
yes they have a conflict and they're
prioritizing resources there. The
Chinese are an incredible rival in space
right now. Yes they don't have the same
reusable launch capabilities that SpaceX
and others have. what they do put in
space, even if they brute force it there
with hypergal powered thrusters or
hypergall powered rockets akin to like
Titan 2 of decades past, what goes in
space is good. And I think there were
some pretty uh interesting developments
that came out of AFA today that our
secretary of air force and others in the
space force said that enlightened uh I
think the general public about how
contested that environment is. The
bottom line is the Chinese are extremely
good in space right now. You couple that
with some Russian capabilities on
nuclear power, they will return to the
moon and they will get to the moon and
they will build a base on the south
pole.
>> And where would we be if we didn't have
SpaceX in relation to China?
>> I mean, SpaceX is our are I mean,
they're they're incredible. I mean,
they're our most important uh launch
partner. We can't send astronauts to and
from the space station without them. We
can't have down mass of our science
experiments from the space station
without them. The the the Nancy Grace
Roman telescope that's going out to
pursue the secrets of the m of the
universe was launched on a Falcon Heavy
not that long ago. We are fortunate.
There's a lot of great companies in
commercial space right now, but I mean
the United States would be uh seriously
challenged in the in the high ground of
space without their capabilities. Jared,
I'm not a huge fan of government. Uh but
I think NASA plays one of the most
important roles for humanity that no
individual organization outside of
government can play. I cannot think of a
better person to lead it. I think you're
an inspiration to so many. Absolutely.
And I I truly honestly respect your
service that that you've provided to
this country and to the world. We're so
lucky to have you. Thank you for being
here.
>> Oh, grateful every day. Thank you all.
Thank you. [applause]
Don't forget your book. Yeah.
Thanks.
>> Thanks for coming.
>> Thanks, man. Thank you. Appreciate